Stanford University
All right, I was going to talk about the
second law of thermodynamics, which I
don't remember if I talked about it all
or not. Did we Did we talk about the
second law?
But this is but um
Remind me, did we talk about the second
law? And
No. Yeah, we
we could have gone there or to black
hole entropy, I think. All right, so
let's let's right. So, let's talk about
the second law of thermodynamics.
It's a very tricky law.
On the one hand, it says that
a certain something
associated with the system always
increases.
On the other hand, Newton's laws of
motion
are reversible.
Any trajectory
can be reversed and is another possible
trajectory
where just everything runs backward with
the movie runs backward.
Uh
What do you have to do? Supposing I pick
a solution of Newton's equations. Again,
let's take
X and P. That's a phase space in our
very simple system with one coordinate
and one momentum. What is
the trajectory of a system in the phase
space?
Supposing we start over here at some
instant of time and follow the system
and it goes to here.
That's a particular
trajectory of the system.
Early times, late times, and it goes
this way.
There is another trajectory of the
system, which is the time reversed
trajectory. Is it just a trajectory from
here to here?
Not quite.
Not quite. And the reason is that in
order to reverse the trajectory, you
have to reverse the velocity.
So, a trajectory which goes from here to
here
in order to find the inverse trajectory,
the time reverse of it, you have to
start with the object going in the
opposite velocity. So, that means you
have to reflect all velocities, which
mean reflect all momenta.
There's another trajectory.
Let's see if I can draw this.
Which looks like that, which is just a
reflection. And the reflection just
means that at every point along the
trajectory, it's running with the
opposite velocity.
You know, if you see a movie and you see
a car going over a certain velocity and
you run the movie backward, the car is
going with the opposite velocity. But
it's But other than the fact that the
velocity is reversed,
Newton's equations are completely
reversible. And so, for example, if
there's a trajectory of a many particle
system where the particles start off in
the corner of the room over here
and then move to fill up the entire
system and come to thermal equilibrium
and after a time of order a few seconds
or something, well, probably longer than
that, but after a time of a few hours,
the
the molecules distribute themselves in
thermal equilibrium,
then if we could get into that system
and reverse the motion of every
molecule,
in other words, change the sign of its
velocity and run it,
it would, according to Newton's
equations, just run backward and all the
molecules go back into the corner.
And nobody ever sees that.
And it seems to violate it does violate
the second law of thermodynamics.
So, what's going on? How can it be that
Newton's equations are time reversible
and the second law of thermodynamics is
a complete one-way job? It tells you
that systems always go in one direction
and never in the other direction.
This was an extremely confusing point
um
that
was sorted out relatively late, you
know, in the last 30 years or so.
Uh Boltzmann had much of the right
ideas,
but uh he didn't quite clinch it and it
took some time.
The key is the idea of chaos. The key is
the idea of chaos. So, let's talk
And of course, the answer is
that
not that this can't happen
and the system go to some very unlikely
state.
It's just that it's unlikely for the
system to go to an unlikely state. So, a
sudden reversal of entropy
of
a system going from a maximally
disordered state in which all the
particles are in random positions filled
up this volume here to a highly ordered
state where all the molecules are in the
same corner of the room. That's not
impossible. It's just very unlikely.
So, we have to understand better if we
want to understand the second law of
thermodynamics, we have to understand
the system the way systems move in phase
space.
Uh because
that is what it's all about.
How systems evolve in phase space.
Now again, phase space is
multi-dimensional.
And I will have to represent it just
necessarily because we don't have enough
dimensions on the blackboard, we will
have to represent it as just
two-dimensional, P and X. Well, X and P.
Now, there is a rule in phase space
about the way systems evolve. If you
start
with a lump. Let's start with a lump in
phase space. There's a lump, a nice
round lump. It's not particularly round,
but a nice round lump in phase space.
What does that mean? That means all of
the possible starting points
in this lump here
and evolve them, evolve each one of
them,
the lump
evolves into some other shape.
Follow each point in the phase space
with time. It evolves into another
shape.
What's the rule about the evolution of
the of the the lump in phase space?
Equal volume.
Now,
if you have a lump. Now, what a lump
means is a probability distribution. And
let's just take it for simplicity to be
the probability distribution which is
zero on the outside of the lump and and
not one, but constant on the inside of
the lump.
All right, so it's a probability
distribution which tells you no more and
no less than the system is in the lump.
And the lump evolves
and after a time, all you know is that
the system is some place in the
displaced or evolved lump.
What is the entropy
of This is a problem This is a
probability distribution.
Okay. This is a probability
distribution. And so, it has an entropy
associated with it.
The entropy
is logarithm of the number of states
that are in the probability
distribution.
Yes, the if the probability distribution
is flat over some set of states,
then the probability is simply logarithm
of the number. But wait a minute, we
can't quite say that when the
probability when the states are
continuous like this, the number of
states in there is quite infinite,
continuously infinite. And so, in
classical physics, again, we divide the
phase space into little cells
and the right statement is that the
entropy is proportional to the volume to
the logarithm of the volume. Did I say
the logarithm of the volume in phase
space?
That's the classical analog of the
logarithm of the number of states, the
logarithm of the volume.
And the volume is conserved as the
system moves as the system moves.
So, as time goes on, no matter what
the system does,
the
lump in phase space has exactly the same
volume that it started with.
The implication is that the entropy,
since it's just the logarithm of the
volume in phase space, stays the same.
But that's not consistent with what we
know about the way systems behave.
Entropy increases.
So, we can state the puzzle either
through the puzzle of reversibility,
that what goes one way can go the other
way.
That seems to be inconsistent with the
law of increase of entropy. But we can
state it another way, through the
principle that the volume in phase space
is constant with time. And that says
that the the volume's constant, the
logarithm of the volume is constant, and
the entropy simply can't change.
Whatever the probability distribution
is, the entropy can't change. So, where
What is What is the meaning of the
second law of thermodynamics?
And to understand that, we have to first
have an idea of what chaos is.
Chaos
To illustrate chaos, my favorite example
is a billiard table.
But let's make an idealized frictionless
billiard table
with no pockets, please. No holes in the
billiard
Everybody's played three-cushion
billiards, right? You know that there
are billiard tables that don't have
holes in them.
Right? So, we got away
But we'll put a whole bunch of billiard
balls in.
We have all the numbered balls 1 through
15 plus the cue ball.
Cue ball's over here.
Eight eight ball over here, seven ball
over here, and the cue ball.
All right. Now, they're all in perfectly
at rest. It's a completely frictionless
billiard table. The cushions are
perfectly perfectly reflecting. They're
not made of rubber, they're made of the
perfectly reflecting
cushions. And so, it's an idealized
dissipationless This is the game of
dissipationless
billiards.
All right? And we shoot the cue ball at
a very definite angle, at a very
definite velocity, extremely precise.
The laws of mechanics tell us that the
system will follow in a deterministic
way a trajectory which is infinitely
predictable if we know the the initial
condition with perfect exactitude.
All right? But,
what happens if we make a tiny mistake
in the direction that we shoot the
billiard ball in?
Well,
a tiny mistake here, instead of sending
this billiard ball off this way, will
send it off at a slightly different
angle.
It'll reflect.
This one reflects over here.
And as you can kind of see, the
Now, this one might hit this ball where
this one not hit that ball.
And boy, then really the evolution after
that point is entirely different.
Okay.
Errors, small errors or small deviations
in the initial conditions build up
exponentially for most systems.
Now, there are special systems where
this doesn't happen. Let's just take one
billiard ball
on a square billiard table.
Then, the motion
Or even better, a one-dimensional
billiard.
One-dimensional billiard, and we shoot
the ball this way with a certain
velocity, it just goes back and forth
and back and forth, and there's nothing
to There's no There's nothing to build
up exponentially.
All right? This is quite stable.
But, most systems, almost all systems,
are chaotic. Chaotic means exceedingly
sensitive to the initial conditions in
such a way that two initial conditions
which are close together in phase space
will start exponentially deviating from
each other.
All right. So, if we take two points in
phase space,
and we follow them, they're very close,
we follow them, they exponentially
depart from each other.
All right. So, the distance between
those between these two points,
let's say the initial separation was
just epsilon. The initial separation is
epsilon.
Then, after a time, the separation will
be epsilon times e
to a
number, I'll call it delta,
times t.
That delta depends on the system. It may
even depend on where you are in the
phase space, but in general,
it's a number
that exponentially increases the
separation between phase points. If
epsilon is exactly zero to begin with,
the separation after time delta t is
also zero.
But, if epsilon is a small
very small number, but non-zero, then in
not too long a time, depending on this
delta here, the separation will become
large.
Once it becomes large, they go off on
their own way, and they they don't the
trajectories don't resemble each other.
This number here is called an exponent,
or it's called a Lyapunov exponent.
Lyapunov.
Oh, boy.
You win, I think.
Yep. Yep.
Lyapunov exponent. And it just
represents the degree of instability.
It's always It's It's generally
positive.
And away you go.
Okay. Now, how can this be consistent
with the statement that the that the
phase space volume stays fixed? If all
points sort of Whoops. If all points
sort of deviate from each other
exponentially, how is it that the phase
space volume doesn't grow?
Okay. How come it doesn't grow? What
happens is a little bit different. It's
not that it grows.
It separates into a kind of fractal. So,
let me try to Let me try to draw
roughly speaking what happens in a
chaotic system.
You start with a phase space blob which
is nice and regular.
And you evolve. Well, it starts to get
a more complicated shape, and it starts
to grow tentacles
or filaments to form a filamentary
structure
where the filaments
get kind of narrow,
but the total volume doesn't change. You
go a little further, and the filaments
start to break up into very narrow
lots of them.
Oh, god. I I I I hesitate to try to draw
it.
It becomes a kind of very complicated
fractal with exactly the same volume as
it started with,
but with a shape which sort of spreads
out its tentacles.
So, it's like a piece of cotton wool,
you know, a piece of large piece of
cotton. Yeah. If it's connected, it
stays connected. If it's connected, it
stays connected.
If it's connected, it stays connected.
Yeah. The topology does not change.
If it's simply connected, it stays
simply connected. If it's multiply
connected, it stays multiply connected.
Uh but,
no matter how you start in a chaotic
system,
it starts to grow tentacles, and the
tentacles
cause the phase space blob
to sort of spread all over the place,
and not only spread all over the place,
but in a certain sense get very dense.
Now, its volume does not increase.
So, it's like a piece of great big fuzzy
cotton that could fill this whole room
even though its volume, if you were to
squeeze it down
so that you were actually looking at the
volume of actual material, might be
small.
Okay.
That's the way things evolve evolve in
phase space.
Okay. Yeah.
What happens when it gets thinner than
the Planck length?
Well, okay. We We then we have to deal
with quantum mechanics. And And
incidentally,
um
the Planck unit
Planck's constant. Forget Planck length.
We're not getting into a quantum gravity
at the moment. So, forget Planck length.
But, Planck I think you meant Planck's
constant. Yeah. Okay. Planck's constant
is a unit of area, not a unit of length.
Planck's constant is a unit of momentum
times length. So, it's a unit of area in
the phase space.
Okay.
So,
um
It's a It's a It's a proper question,
but at the moment we're doing purely
classical physics where Planck's length
or Planck's constant corresponds to an
infinitely small uh
an infinitely small volume or infinitely
small area in phase space. So, there's
no In classical physics, you never get
to the Planck
size.
Now, to do quantum mechanics, you have
to do quantum mechanics. And there's
there is a version of this in quantum
mechanics, but uh
uh this is the classical version.
Okay. So,
the phase space volume gets very
complicated, but without changing its
its volume in phase space.
On the other hand, we should take into
account, and we should always take into
account, that in general, our ability to
distinguish points in phase space is
limited.
All right?
Not just limited because because the
bathtub full of hot water just has a
given temperature and not much else, but
even if we had microscopes that could
see every particle, there still would be
a limitation
uh or we should assume that there is a
limitation on the
on our ability to resolve those points.
Whatever that ability is, let's
represent it
by a small little
cell. Not a cell, a small little blob in
phase space, which is itself much
smaller than the original blob.
And let's just say every point in this
phase space
is replaced
by a blob of that big.
In other words, we can't We can't
distinguish one point in the blob one
point in the in the mini blob from
another.
And so, we just fill it up like that.
All right. We're going to
Since these blobs are a little bit
coarse-grained,
they might actually make the volume, if
we replace every point on the inside by
one of these small blobs, it will
increase the volume a little bit.
Just because they each point on the
boundary here
will be spread out a little bit. But, on
the whole, that won't be much of an
effect as long as the blob is a nice
regular blob like this. Okay? So, if you
start with a nice regular blob,
the volume in phase of the coarse grain,
this is called coarse graining, coarse
graining the phase space,
means looking at the phase space as a
collection of coarse grained little
areas like this.
Coarse graining a nice smooth
configuration in phase space doesn't
change its volume significantly.
But,
as this starts to blossom more and more
tentacles,
you can see what starts to happen. I
should Let me Let me try to draw this in
a way which um
makes clear what begins to happen. Okay.
So, eventually we get to a configuration
where
it just bristles out structure,
very, very thin filaments
in every direction in the phase space.
And now let's coarse grain
the evolved
blob. If I coarse grain the evolved
blob,
well, first of all, it gets big.
It gets big not because its volume
increases,
but because it just grows enormously
long tentacles
of very, very thin
regions of phase space.
And
Yeah. The The
The coarse graining blobs are too big to
distinguish between the different
branches of this fractal.
And so, what happens when you coarse
grain it
is it gets
much bigger.
Just like a large cotton ball, if we
replaced each fiber of the cotton by a
thicker fiber,
then
the volume of the cotton would be much
bigger than the original starting volume
where it was compressed down to
something small.
Okay?
In fact, it will get about as big as
this whole uh structure, this whole
multi-tentacled
structure.
It'll all get sort of filled in by the
coarse graining.
It really doesn't matter very much how
much coarse graining you do. In other
words, what the volume of these coarse
grained little cells is. Eventually,
this thing gets so
fractalized. I don't know what the right
word. There must be a verb that goes
with uh being
uh fractalized. All right, I invent the
verb. Fractalized. It becomes so
fractalized that when it's coarse
grained, it uh it will always grow.
So, now we have to distinguish
between
the fine grained entropy and the coarse
grained entropy. The fine grained
entropy is the exact logarithm of the
volume of the phase space keeping track
of the infinite fine grained structure
of phase space. That never increases.
That is frozen by Liouville's theorem.
On the other hand, this more physically
useful coarse grained
phase space,
a coarse grained phase space where the
distinctions between very, very close
points are blurred over, that volume
does grow.
So, the logarithm of the coarse grained
volume increases. It's the coarse
grained volume that defines the
thermally the conventional entropy
of thermodynamics.
And you see, there is really not a um a
uh contradiction. Now, let's go back.
Let's suppose this system evolves into
this system over here. Or much more
complicated than the system over here.
Let's just complicate it by putting a
lot more structure into it.
All this fibrous.
All right. Now, what about when we go
backward? Let's come back to the
question of running the system backward.
Okay?
This might represent all the particles
off in the corner of a room. This might
represent what happens to those
particles when they fill up uh the
volume of space.
Okay? Let's run the system backward.
Here's the rule. Here's what we know.
If we start on any one of the tentacles,
on any one of the fibers,
right? We will trace back
to here.
But on the other hand, if we start
nearby
one of the fibers, the fibers have
gotten so thin
that this chaotic behavior, the Lyapunov
exponent here,
instead, whereas this point over here
might have traced back to here, this
point neighboring to it will trace back
for a while and then go off to some
wildly different place.
Lesson is that yes, if you did literally
reverse every particle exactly after the
particles had left the corner of the
room, they would go back to the corner.
But make the tiniest mistake in one
particle,
after a couple of collisions, the system
will have essentially lost memory of the
fact that it was just a time reverse of
this very unlikely state that you
started with. And what will it do? It'll
just continue to fill up the room with
uh with particles. Okay?
So,
yes, it is possible to reverse the law
of entropy, but the likelihood is
extremely small. This whole blob of
phase space here, this whole coarse
grained blob of phase space is very big.
Most of the points look a lot like each
other.
And it's only a terribly tiny fraction
of it that traces back to this extremely
unlikely state. Most of it leads
to configurations which are even bigger
and spread out even larger.
That's the second law. That's the nature
of the second law.
That Yeah. The two points you're talking
about that are close to each other,
they're both within one of the uh
filaments.
No, no, no, no, no, no. One of them's
outside the filament and the other's
inside the filament. Right. If they were
both inside the filament, they would
both lead back. They might lead back to
different points here.
All right? So, if they were both in the
filament or in rather distant pieces of
the filament, they would lead back to
the same blob here.
But if one of them, and remember these
filaments are very fine now, extremely
fine, and so, even if one point is just
tiny minute distance outside the
filament, with time, the exponential
growth in the error will lead you to
some wildly different point in the phase
space.
Most of those points that that this
filamentary This This coarse grained
filament will lead to
will be of yet larger entropy.
In other words, if you follow them
either backward or forward, it doesn't
matter. Let's follow backward. Uh if you
follow backward, this point will go to
here. This point will go to here. But
this point over here will go out to
here.
So, if you follow all the points in this
filamentary structure backward, you will
not get most of these points back into
this tiny little volume here of phase
space. They will go off and make yet an
even more complicated filamentary
structure.
The second law goes Yeah.
Sorry. I have a question.
Would you say that if you actually did
the full integral of that whole filament
spider spider web, that you would always
get the original volume, but that really
you can't
I'm not sure what integral you want to
do. If you integral over the whole phase
space, the implication of integrating
over phase space is that you can go to
every
integrating, you can go to every
uh point of phase space and retrace it
back exactly.
Whereas if you're summing, then you're
sort of coarse graining kind of.
Yeah, when you when you when you sum,
you're effectively cross
you're effectively coarse graining the
phase space. So, the amount of coarse
graining is related to the sizes of your
delta x's. It is. It is. It is. But it
hardly matters. The answer is that
hardly matters uh how much coarse
graining you do. This filamentary
structure grows so quickly and gets so
dense
that uh that it doesn't matter very much
uh
what the size of the coarse graining is.
It'll define a blob whose size is pretty
much independent of the size of the
coarse graining.
Just because
these coarse grained fiber these fine
grained fibers here get very, very close
together, it hardly matters what your
coarse graining size is.
The result of coarse graining will be to
fill up
uh
the whole volume of this branched
structure. Yeah.
In that picture of the guy jumping off
the diving board into the pool,
Yes. Okay. If he goes If he ends up
going back onto the diving board,
being pushed out by the molecules of the
water in the pool, Yeah.
Does that violate any basic law of
physics? No, violates no basic law of
physics other than it's extremely
unlikely
because just one little molecular
accident of the wrong kind
uh will completely undo So, one little
molecular accident means a slight shift
in the initial conditions will simply
lead him plop back into the water.
That when I knocked about the billiard
ball one, and I think somebody
calculated that, did you?
What's that again?
Oh.
To change the orbits of uh
Of the trajectory of
Oh, sure.
Yeah, just a just a butterfly waving its
wings a thousand miles away can uh
Yes, yes, yes, yes. Yes. Yes. Yeah, no,
no.
Yeah, it does. It does. It does.
Um if you follow this blob
forward
it'll increase its volume.
Follow it backward
in detail
from each point within the fibrous
structure and the volume will decrease.
But coarse-grain it
now you're going backward. You're going
backward in time, but following the
system backward in time it'll still
increase the volume of phase space when
you go backward.
So, the second law of thermodynamics
would work in both directions. Start
with an initial configuration run it
forward, run it backward. The most
likely thing to happen is that entropy
will increase.
So, then what is the meaning of the fact
that entropy
increases
uh in one direction and not the other?
The meaning of it is that the world
started with a very low entropy for
reasons that have to do with cosmology
and that we don't completely know.
For some reason
the world started in a state of very low
entropy. Why? Nobody knows because
nobody knows that much about the initial
state of the universe and why it was so
started. But what we do know is that the
entropy was very low. That means we
started out in a very tiny blob of the
phase space.
Uh if we ran it backward, that blob
would expand. If we run it forward, that
blob would expand.
But
the fact is
cosmologically, we know that the
universe started in a very ordered small
volume of phase space. So, the second
law of thermodynamics also entails
something about initial conditions that
the universe didn't start
in a in a
in a random configuration. It started
in the analog of all the molecules off
in the corner of the room.
And then they spread out.
That's not exactly that that of course
is just an analogy.
So, yes
the the meaning of the second law of
thermodynamics is among other things
that the initial conditions were a
configuration
of very low entropy analogous to all of
the molecules in the room
being in the corner.
Well, actually not. Um if the actually
not.
No not really. No, this is not
predicated. This is just predicated on
the idea of chaos.
Um
This does not mean the system comes to
thermal equilibrium.
That's not the implication of this.
It just means that you spread out and
lose memory of where you started. It
doesn't say that the system's energy
levels are populated with certain
probabilities.
Okay?
Uh that's a that's a separate story.
Right.
Yeah.
What we can distinguish. What what what
Yeah, I think it's I think it really
does correspond to a um
But the main point is that the degree of
coarse-graining is not very important
because eventually
no matter how small a coarse-graining
is, no matter how small these
coarse-grained volumes are, in not too
long a time these branches will get
within that will get
closer together than that volume. The
smaller we make it, the longer the time
it will take for the branches to get the
that close together, but it's not the
it doesn't depend very much on the
nature of the coarse-graining.
And so, pretty much independently of the
detailed numbers of the coarse-graining,
just wait not too long and the
coarse-graining will fill up the whole
volume. Now, of course
there is a degree of course of
fine-graining or coarse-graining
which is so precise
that
that it will not get filled in. But then
just wait a little longer and it will
get filled in.
Look, this is classical physics. If we
want to do quantum mechanics, we have to
do quantum mechanics. So, we have to we
have to get into what quantum chaos
means and we have to get into what
uh
uh and that's that's already a separate
subject. So, this is classical physics.
That's that's that's for the matter of
time for Yeah.
Yeah, but it's not very sensitive.
You could.
Remember, exponentials get big very
fast. Right? So, if this Lyapunov
coefficient here
is not very small
what the what corresponds to what here?
This
distance between neighboring points
which we might think of as the
coarse-graining is this epsilon here.
How far apart they get from each other
is epsilon e to the delta t.
So, two points which are close
will get far very quickly and that means
that this branching structure grows very
fast.
It grows very very fast, exponentially
And yes, it's true that given a time
scale given a time, a thousand years I
can prescribe the coarse-graining to be
fine-grained enough
so that your coarse-graining will not
fill up the
the fractal structure here. Will not
What's the right words? You know, smoosh
it out.
Okay?
But on the other hand
given a degree of coarse-graining as a
general rule, very very quickly that
coarse-graining will
will will be sufficient to smoosh the
phase space.
Yeah, it gets That's right. It gets
That's right. It becomes constant after
a while.
Right.
Uh on or okay, up to a point.
Energy is conserved.
Okay? So, you cannot fill up the phase
space. If you start with a if you start
with a phase space blob being
concentrated at some energy.
All right. So, what does it really look
like? What it really looks like is in
phase space there are surfaces of given
energy.
There's a surface of a given energy in
the phase space. Really, this whole
discussion should take place on the
surface.
So, starting on the surface with a blob
the surface we will not get off the
surface. That's just energy
conservation. But on the surface, the
blob will
begin to do this um
fractalating behavior.
So, apart from the conservation law of
energy
yeah, after a while this thing will
really cover the phase space uh very
uniformly.
Yeah.
With this very very intricate fine uh
threads of uh
Well, you lose information you lose
information not because some fundamental
law is not predictive but because of the
fine-graining. Yeah, I mean so,
information now
when you speak about information, you
have to decide whether you're talking
about fine-grained information or
coarse-grained information.
Fine-grained information, you never
lose.
Coarse-grained information, yes, you do
lose it and you lose it in just this
way.
So, that distinction has to be made. It
always has to be made.
Uh
Well, okay. So, um
the time scale
13.7 billion years is not the long
enough. That's all. What is the right
time scale? The right time scale is
probably about 40 billion year about No,
more like a hundred billion years.
But it's exponential. Hm? The that this
divergence is exponential.
Universe is very big. You start all all
the molecules in the corner of the room.
If the room is big enough,
it will take a long time for them to
fill up the room.
But it won't take a long time for the
entropy to start to increase. This
tentacle structure here
still
hasn't grown to fill up the whole phase
space.
So, how big is the phase space? The
phase space is very big and it takes a
long time to get filled up.
But still, the entropy starts increasing
long before this thing fills up the
whole phase space.
And the critical way is dendritic
growth. Is what dendritic
Dendritic growth, yeah. Is it fractal
structure? Yeah.
Yeah, it's a similar to that. It's quite
similar to that. Right.
Right.
Yeah. But it's not just a fractal, but
it's a space-filling fractal.
A space-filling fractal which really
doesn't fill the fine-grained space, but
fills the coarse-grained space. Yeah.
And it's not so easy to do that. Well,
it's not so easy to picture it. But
that's that's roughly what happens.
You emphasize the initial conditions
as being the
Somebody mentioned exactly. Say it
again.
You emphasize the initial conditions as
being the thing we don't know exactly,
but we never know the Hamiltonian
exactly.
Right. Right. Right. Right. That's
that's another point, yeah. If if
halfway if if after we started, let's
say we started here and we got to here.
And now we want to time reverse it,
but we're going to time reverse it with
a slightly different Hamiltonian.
Doesn't go back to here. It It does It
does essentially the same thing as what
would happen if you displace the point a
little bit.
So, yeah. A slight change in the laws of
physics could completely undo the
ability to to reverse the um
Wouldn't you just coarse-graining result
in a violation of the fine conservation
of information?
No, coarse-graining well So, information
destroyed is coarse-grained.
Yeah, information is destroyed if it's
coarse-grained. That's not a violation
of the
Of the conservation of information. No,
the conservation of information is the
theorem that says that the fine-grained
entropy never increases.
Right.
So, that's the that's the big
distinction. Fine-grained versus
coarse-grained. The very very precise
equations of of
of mechanics
say that the volume of phase space
doesn't increase.
And it's you know
And doesn't increase or decrease.
Incidentally,
um
you can imagine laws of physics
in which the volume of phase space
shrinks. Not too hard to imagine laws of
physics where a blob in phase space
would be allowed to shrink. It's not
allowable in standard classical
mechanics.
But we could imagine differential
equations which sort of
push things together. That would
correspond to the Lyapunov coefficient
being negative
and things sort of
coming together. That would violate the
second law of thermodynamics. In a world
like that, the second law of
thermodynamics would not be true.
Uh so,
um
it's not a law which is true for all
possible differential equations. It's a
law which is true for those differential
equations which result from standard
mechanics.
You can imagine systems with negative
Lyapunov
I'm trying to
understand the size of this
of this little coarse-grained
It's two Yeah. in terms of entropy like
dS equals change in energy divided by
temperature. That's a pretty much a
fixed formula.
Does this You said a moment ago that
it's not very sensitive to the size of
of that
Like we have two objects and you you
divide you divide you put them together
and they reach the same temperature. So,
the entropy goes up.
How how does the size of that little
fine grain come into play there? Is that
too close It does a little It does a
little bit in the formula for entropy.
Uh
actually, it's an additive constant.
It's an additive constant. It's an
additive constant. Um
You know what it's connected to? It's
connected to the same issue of of
replacing integrals by uh by sums.
And
replacing the integral by the sum uh
worst adds a constant to the entropy.
Uh
so, when we talked last week about the
entropy of black holes, we're talking
about a coarse-grained entropy. Mhm.
Absolutely.
Yeah. And in fact, in all of statistical
mechanics and in thermodynamics, the
entropy that's being talked about is
coarse-grained.
In information theory, one sometimes
speaks about the fine-grained entropy.
Uh but in in statistical mechanics and
thermodynamics, entropy means
coarse-grained entropy.
Right.
So, it means the coarse-grained
or logarithm of the coarse-grained
volume in phase space.
Okay, this is this is a a deep and
profound point that puzzled people for
many years.
And um
and I think it's more or less resolved.
This behavior, this chaotic behavior.
I'm not exactly sure what the difference
is between something called mixing and
something called and what's called
chaos.
I uh mixing I think is the idea that
this branched
tentacle structure covers the whole
phase space pretty uniformly.
Chaos is a little bit weaker, I think. I
think it just says that the trajectories
um
uh
separate.
This is thing is called mixing.
Uh but they're closely related and I'm
not sure if there is a difference
between them or not. I've never been
clear about that.
Uh
what the difference between mixing and
and uh and chaos is, if any if any.
But briefly in the typical of quantum
mechanics, wouldn't it be parameters of
quantum mechanics give a
uh
a a
definition of the degree of
coarse-graining? Yeah, Planck's
constant. Yeah. Yeah, sure. Planck's
constant. You can't make it smaller than
Planck's constant. Absolutely.
But the reason that I'm saying that um
yeah.
You see, if you replace
the sum by the integral,
well, that's that's this h bar to a
power here. h bar h bar to the n.
That's the little cell in phase space.
Little cell in phase space. What happens
if you multiply the integral by the
partition function by a small
uh cell size?
Well, all it does is add a constant to
the logarithm of the partition function.
I just multiply the partition function
by this coarse-graining here, which just
replaces d3px by you know, it's this
business of the difference between the
sum times the volume element and the
integral itself.
That's just a numerical constant in the
entropy and doesn't affect anything very
significant in the thermodynamics.
But wouldn't you need to factor for the
uncertainty by the small amount?
You need The only thing you really Well,
okay. In quantum mechanics, when you're
thinking about real quantum mechanics,
yeah, this this thing does matter. But
in discussing the classical limit of
quantum mechanics, in the classical
limit, this just factors out as a as an
all over multiplicative factor in the
partition function, approximately. To
the extent that you can replace sums by
integrals,
this just factors out as a
multiplicative constant. And when you
take the logarithm, it's just an
additive constant. An additive constant
in the in the free energy and in the
entropy.
Okay? So, it's not a it's not a
significant uh
uh
thing.
No other questions about the second law?
Okay, that's uh
that's
All right, we have 20 minutes.
Let's do some Is that right? Is this the
Yeah, that's the correct correct time.
We have 20 minutes.
And in the 20 minutes, I want to start
some quan- We actually did some quantum
statistical mechanics, didn't we? We did
the problem of the rotor and quantized
the angular momentum.
Uh that had to do with this funny
paradox about complex or structured
molecules, why the structure disappears
at low temperature,
why you don't have the equipartition of
energy distributed among all the various
modes of motion of a molecule,
why you can pretend molecules are point
molecules. I want to do another example
of it.
And this example
has many many applications.
It is nothing but the harmonic
oscillator.
We didn't do this, did we? We didn't do
the quantum the quantum oscillator. In
fact, I don't even think we did the
classical oscillator.
Okay.
Let's suppose that a molecule
has the structure of a harmonic
oscillator.
In other words, the internal degrees of
freedom are described by an oscillation
of some kind. Not the overall motion of
the of the molecule. The overall motion
of the molecule, its center of mass
motion, it still moves exactly as it did
in the uh point molecule case.
But the internal structure of the
molecule is just described by an
oscillation. We haven't done that yet.
Again,
we can start classical and see how much
energy we expect to be stored in the
oscillations.
So, let's do that.
Let's take the case of Now, this is a
fictitious molecule.
And the fictitious molecule is just two
points on a spring.
Described by a Hamiltonian or an energy
function which is just P squared over
twice some mass parameter.
It's not the overall mass of the
molecule. It might be some What what's
it called? The the relative mass, some
reduced mass. It could be the reduced
mass of the two particles.
And it oscillates about its center of
mass. But whatever it does, this is the
kinetic energy of the motion of the
molecule. And then there's a potential
energy. And the potential energy is the
amount by which the molecule is
stretched. It's proportional to some
spring constant which we call K.
K squared.
K squared X squared. Where X is not the
position. K squared X squared over two.
X is not the position of the center of
mass of the molecule. It's just a
coordinate which describes the
oscillations. So, let us not confuse it.
I could have given it different names.
But I don't have you know, I'd rather
just call it P squared plus X squared.
K. Sorry. K.
Thank you.
K.
So, this molecule is now an oscillator.
In the limit that K becomes very large,
that's the limit of an extremely stiff
spring.
It becomes prohibitively expensive to
stretch the spring by by the spring by
any finite amount.
So, you might expect that in that limit,
when K becomes enormously large, that
the molecule would behave like a point
molecule. It'll become exceedingly
difficult to excite any significant
amount of vibration
because
the spring constant is so large.
And that should be right. I mean, if
anything is right about
about molecular physics,
then that should be right. That
that internal structure
should be frozen out at very low
temperatures in particular.
All right. Let's let's just imagine now
the statistical mechanics of a single
harmonic oscillator in thermal
equilibrium.
Let's focus on just one molecule. And
let's focus let's forget the center of
mass motion.
That we know how to deal with.
That's just the usual description of the
molecular motion. Let's just focus on
the internal vibrations of the molecule.
And to do that,
we just think of the molecule or its
internal motions as a system in thermal
equilibrium with everything else.
And the probability distribution
for the Ps and the Xs is just governed
again by the Maxwell-Boltzmann
distribution. Now, just a single
molecule, a single X and a single P.
And the partition function for that
single molecule is just the integral DX
DP.
E to the minus beta, where beta is
inverse temperature as always,
times
P squared over 2M
plus KX squared over two.
Now, before I go and calculate this, let
me just
point out one connection.
What's the frequency of this harmonic
oscillator?
The frequency of vibration, omega.
Square root of K over M. You can do that
by solving Newton's equations. Newton's
equations are F equals MA.
The force is KX.
Mass times X double dot.
And you can see that the important
quantity is K over M by dividing by M.
That's the frequency. K over M, square
root of K over M is the frequency.
All right. So, let's keep track of that.
Frequency of the oscillator, omega
equals square root of K over M.
Now,
here's the partition function.
It's easy to compute. We've done this
sort of thing before. The two
integrations, notice that in the
exponent, the P squareds and the X
squareds add.
That means that this factor is a
product. It's a product of E to the
minus beta P squared over 2M.
E to the minus beta
K
X squared over two.
And the integrals also the integral is
also a factorized structure, DX and DP
or DP
integral DX.
Just two separate factorized integrals.
All right. We know how to do this
integral. We've done this integral
before. Anybody remember what it is?
Just a P integration.
Well, it's not quite the square root of
pi.
It's the square root of pi times 2M
2 pi M over beta.
Right?
That's what this integral is.
You have to change variables to get the
2 pi. The change variables so that this
is just E to the minus X squared or this
E to the minus something squared.
We've done that integral.
And it's just the square root of 2M pi
divided by beta.
The important thing here is the beta
dependence, but let's track the whole
thing.
Now, what about this integral?
This integral is exactly the same kind
of integral.
Except instead of integrating over P,
we're integrating over X. Well, X is
just an integration variable. That
doesn't matter.
And the only difference is that whereas
you had a mass in the denominator here,
you have a spring constant in the
numerator here.
So, I can read immediately read off that
the answer is
2 pi.
And instead of M in the numerator, we'll
have K in the denominator.
And that's it.
That's the partition function for one
harmonic oscillator. And that all
together is equal to 2
pi over beta
times square root of M over K.
But that's just one over omega.
That's the partition function. Really
easy.
Classical partition function.
What's its logarithm? Log of Z
is equal to
log
of 2 pi over omega.
Those are constants. Omega is a fixed
constant.
Plus or minus
log beta.
What is the energy? Oh, incidentally,
minus log of Z, which is the thing that
we differentiate.
What is the average energy of the
oscillator?
It's the derivative of minus log Z with
respect to beta.
That's just one over beta.
So, the energy of this oscillator
is just one over beta, which is just the
temperature.
Not a half the temperature, not three
halves the temperature, but just the
temperature.
The reason it's one times a temperature
and not a half times a temperature is
because there are two integrals here.
You get two factors of the square root
of beta in the denominator. And that
gives you
temperature for the energy.
Notice that it doesn't depend on the
spring constant.
The partition function depends on the
spring constant through omega here.
Incidentally, very very large spring
constant means very large omega. Very
large frequency, very rapid
vibration. On the other hand, no matter
how large omega gets,
the energy stored in that oscillator is
always just T.
So, again, we have the same paradox
again. That no matter how stiff we make
the molecular bonds,
this harmonic oscillator molecule always
stores this much energy in the internal
vibrations. And there does not seem to
be a limit in which it goes over to the
point molecule. The point molecule would
be the situation where the internal
energy was just zero.
You might have expected that when the
spring becomes so stiff,
that the molecule would behave as a
point molecule. And then there would be
no internal energy.
There would still be the energy of
translation, but no energy of vibration.
So, again, the same paradox as with
respect to the rotational motion of an
oscillator.
The solution
And there is a paradox. I mean, our
molecules molecules at low temperature
do behave like point molecules.
Okay, low enough temperatures they do
behave. And this doesn't say
only at high temperatures, it's at every
temperature there's this much energy.
But in fact, it's not true.
The solution is again quantum mechanics.
And so in order to understand it, we
have to think about the quantum
mechanics of the harmonic oscillator.
Now, the quantum mechanics of the
harmonic oscillator
may or may not be known to you in
detail, but I think almost everybody, at
least in this class,
knows the result. And the result is that
the energy levels, and this is all we
need, that the energy levels are
discrete,
and the nth energy level
is
n, n now is an integer,
times h bar
times omega.
Did I leave anything out?
The zero energy. The zero energy. But it
doesn't make any difference because
adding a constant to the energy
doesn't affect anything in statistical
mechanics. You can check that yourself.
Adding a constant would affect no
uh
observable quantity.
Uh
of course it would affect the energy per
uh
it would affect the energy, but that's
only because you added a constant to the
energy. So it will shift all energies by
that same constant.
All right, so that's good enough. That's
good enough for our purposes. And now we
can calculate the partition function of
the quantum oscillator. I think we can
do it in 10 minutes.
Z
is now not an integral, but it's a sum.
And it's a sum over n, all the energy
levels,
of
e to the minus beta
times the energy.
h bar omega times n.
All right, so for example, what is this?
This is one.
That's n equals zero.
The first excited level
plus e to the minus beta h bar omega.
The next level plus e
to the minus twice beta h bar omega, but
I'm going to write that as e to the
minus beta h bar omega squared.
And then plus the same thing cubed and
so forth.
That's what this n does here.
And so the partition function is just
this infinite sum.
The infinite sum this time, unlike the
rotor case,
where what was up here involved n
squared, that was not so much fun,
didn't know how to sum it up. Here we
know how to sum it up. This is a
geometric series.
One plus a constant plus the constant
squared plus the constant cubed. And it
all adds up to
Let's put it over here. One divided by
one minus e to the minus beta h bar
omega.
That's Z.
That's the
That's the oscillator part.
This is just the oscillator. Just the
oscillator.
Do you hear the 2 pi m over beta term?
2 pi
No, this is this this is the full
harmonic This is the harmonic oscillator
classical harmonic oscillator.
This is the quantum harmonic oscillator.
It doesn't doesn't it have
Didn't one of those things come from the
p squared over 2 m? No.
The p squared over 2 m plus the kx
squared over 2 is what's quantized.
Okay. Right. It's the sum of these two
which are quantized.
Remember, this is not the overall
translational motion.
No, it's the sum of them which comes in
discrete levels.
Okay? It is the full energy of the
oscillator.
The oscillator vibrates in
discrete
Right?
Good?
Yeah. Okay.
All right, so here's the partition
function. That's it, it took 2 minutes
to do. And now we can calculate the
average energy and see what the average
energy of the quantum oscillator does
at low temperature and at high
temperature.
And see exactly what it does.
All right, so what do we want to do? We
want to calculate logarithm of Z.
Or minus the logarithm of Z to be
precise. That's what we're interested
in.
And that's equal to the logarithm
of one minus e to the minus beta h bar
omega.
The minus sign came because this thing
is in the denominator, and logarithm of
a denominator involves a negative sign.
Okay, who's strong enough to
differentiate this with respect to beta?
All right, I am.
Superhero will now differentiate.
Okay, first of all, logarithm gives you
one over the argument. One and one over
the thing in the logarithm. One minus e
to the minus beta h bar omega.
Now we have to differentiate the thing
inside here.
All right? The beta diff That That means
differentiate the
exponential here. There's a minus sign
from here.
And now we have to differentiate the
exponential with respect to beta. That's
going to give us another minus sign.
So it'll become plus.
And then just
h bar omega e to the minus beta h bar
omega.
We differentiated with respect to beta,
which gives us the exponential back, but
then h bar omega from differentiating.
You see what it is.
That's the formula.
This is the energy of the harmonic
oscillator
in thermal equilibrium at temperature
one over beta.
It is not exactly It's not in general
equal to the temperature, the
temperature being one over beta, not at
all that. But let's look at it at
different limits.
Let's first look at it in the limit of
high temperature.
In the limit of high temperature,
we expect classical physics. Why do we
expect classical physics at high
temperature?
The reason is that at high temperature,
this tiny little
uh unit of energy that's in the
oscillator is irrelevant.
The energy The oscillator is excited to
such high energy
that it doesn't give a damn that the
energy is quantized in these tiny tiny
little steps.
So we expect the classical answer for
high temperature.
Okay, let's look at it for high
temperature. High temperature means
small beta.
Okay? Did I get uh Did I get this right?
Yeah.
Okay?
No, no beta in the numerator.
No, no beta. Incidentally, I can write
this a little uh
neater. Multiply the top and the bottom
by e to the plus beta h omega.
That'll That'll turn into something a
little bit simpler. h bar omega
If I multiply by e to the plus beta,
this one will go away, and I'll get e to
the beta h bar omega
minus one.
That's a little neater.
Hm? Yeah, minus No, plus.
Plus. Plus. Plus. Plus.
Okay.
Let's look at it at very high
temperature. High temperature means
small beta.
Small beta, we expand the exponential.
We have a small number here. And what's
the exp What's the expansion of e to the
beta h bar omega?
e to the beta h bar omega
is equal to one plus beta h bar omega
plus higher order stuff.
Plus higher order.
All right, the only reason I have to
keep
the first correction here is because the
one cancels.
Okay, so the one cancels.
And after the one is canceled, this is
just h bar omega
divided by beta h bar omega.
The h bar omegas cancel, and one over
beta is temperature.
So at high temperatures, when beta is
small,
we just reproduce the classical
behavior.
So when the temperature is high enough
to be able to excite the discrete
vibrations
of the harmonic oscillator, we reproduce
the situation where the where the
oscillator has temperature t.
But what about low temperatures?
At low temperatures, beta is very large.
e to the beta h omega is very large in
general.
The one can be ignored
in that limit.
This is now low temperatures.
And you can see that the energy in the
oscillator is exponentially small. Beta
is very large at low temperature.
This exponential here is very large.
And the energy in the oscillator is very
very small, exponentially small.
All right, so the oscillator at low
temperatures
is frozen out. It's frozen out by
quantum mechanics.
The h bar omega in the numerator is
insignificant by comparison with the
exponential in the denominator,
exponentially small energy.
Uh And so the internal vibrations, as I
said, are frozen out. Is there anything
else worth saying about this at the
moment?
Um
Well, that is the important thing.
Oh, yeah, one other point. Where is the
crossover?
At high temperatures, it's T.
At low temperatures, it's this
exponentially small thing. Where does it
go? So let's see, what does it look
like?
Uh at small temperatures as a function
of temperature, let's say.
This is extremely small, and it goes to
zero very, very quickly at small
temperatures. Okay? And then
at some point, it takes off and it goes
linearly
like this with temperature.
Somewhere's in here, there's a
transition.
Uh
and it's it's it's not a sharp
transition. It's a sort of spread out
from exponential behavior to linear. But
where does it occur?
It occurs
when
the exponential behavior, when this
exponent gets to be about of order one.
Somewhere's in the vicinity when the
exponential gets to be of order one,
that's where the transition happens.
And that means when beta H bar omega
Well, order one or order two or order
three or some number, not order one
because order one happens when beta is
equal to zero. But at some numerical
value of this exponential, it turns over
and goes from one thing to another. That
means it happens when beta H bar omega
is about equal to one. But what is beta?
Beta is one over temperature.
So what happens when the temperature is
about equal to H bar omega?
In other words, when the temperature is
high enough
that the classical approximation
would allow the system to have one
quantum's worth of energy.
Below that temperature,
the oscillator is frozen. Above that
temperature, it doesn't realize that
it's not a classical harmonic
oscillator, and somewhere's in between
the transition happens.
So that's what tells you at what
temperature the transition between
quantum mechanics and classical
mechanics happen.
The lower the frequency of the
oscillator, the lower the temperature at
which the transition takes place. So if
you have a very floppy oscillator with a
very, very small frequency,
then at low temperatures,
it starts to get excited quite It starts
to the transition happens at the
On the other hand, if you have an
extremely stiff oscillator, it takes a
high temperature before
it starts to behave classically.
All right, that's the basic theory of
the harmonic oscillator, and it governs
just about every system in nature that
we can solve. But in particular, it
governs blackbody radiation. So next
time we'll talk a little bit about
blackbody radiation
and uh get more confusion about
integrals again, I'm sure, because
uh
and we'll we'll discuss blackbody
radiation.
Good.
For more, please visit us at
stanford.edu.